South Boston, Boston, Mass. Phillips Church records, 1823-2003.
Congregational Library & Archives
South Boston, Boston, Mass. Phillips Church records, 1823-2003.
RG1228
Congregational Library & Archives
2.25 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes; 1 oversized file folder)
Phillips Church was founded on December 10, 1823, under the name of "The Evangelical Congregational Church of South Boston" by an Ecclesiastical council of thirteen original members. Services were held in Union Hall on Fourth Street, between B and C Streets, until March 9, 1924, when a small brick church was erected at the corner of Broadway and A street. On March 25, 1834, the church was incorporated. It was named after the first mayor of Boston, John Phillips. A larger wooden church was built in 1836 at the same location on Broadway and A Street. Services were held there until the building was sold in 1858. A new building was erected on Broadway, near Dorchester Street, and the first service was held on November 5, 1858. In 1879, the Church's location on Broadway underwent extensive renovations, and the new edifice was rededicated on December 10. The Phillips Church joined with Conservative Congregational Christian Conference (CCCC) in 1960. The Phillips Church was dissolved circa 2003. The Phillips Church Records collection includes bound volumes of church records, administrative and financial documents, and two scrapbooks containing promotional materials such as programs, correspondence, news clippings, and yearbooks.
Phillips Church (South Boston, Boston, Mass.)
Evangelical Congregational Church (South Boston, Boston, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Congregational Library & Archives prior to August 1963. The Phillips Congregational Church donated two photographs in May 1997. A further aquisition of materials was likely deposited in 2003.
Historical Note
Phillips Church was founded on December 10, 1823, under the name of "The Evangelical Congregational Church of South Boston" by an Ecclesiastical council of thirteen members. The council consisted of three pastors and ten delegates of the Old South, Park Street, and Union Churches of Boston, the First Church of Charlestown, and the Second Church of Dorchester. Rev. Prince Hawes of Glastonbury, Connecticut was appointed as the church's fist pastor and served the church from 1824-1827.
During the Summer of 1823, services were held in Union Hall on Fourth Street, between B and C Streets. The church worshipped there until March 9, 1824, when a small brick church was erected at the corner of Broadway and A street with the financial help of other local churches. The property was held by twelve trustees, four each from Park Street, Old South, and Union Churches.
On March 25, 1834, the Phillips Church Society was incorporated. The name was adopted because it was believed that A Street would soon be renamed Phillips Street, after the first mayor of Boston, John Phillips. The change was never affected, but the church's name remained.
In 1836, a larger wooden church was built at the same location on Broadway and A Street. There was considerable growth of services and membership after relocating to Broadway and A Street. However, on June 13, 1845, the church dismissed fifty-seven members to form the Payson Church. Later, on July 10, 1857, the church dismissed seventy-two members to form the Church of Unity. These churches were later unified into the E Street Church. A Phillips Church member council was formed to discuss the issue of decreasing membership and ultimately decided against dissolution due to the loyalty of existing members. The Broadway and A Street building was sold in 1858. The last service at this location was on July 27, 1958. A new building was erected on Broadway, near Dorchester Street, and the first services were held on November 5, 1858. In 1879, the Church's location on Broadway underwent extensive renovations and the new edifice was rededicated on December 10.
The Phillips Church joined with Conservative Congregational Christian Conference (CCCC) in 1960. The Phillips Church was dissolved circa 2003.
Scope and Contents
This collection focusses on administrative and promotional topics. Administrative records include by-laws, statements of faith, correspondence, meeting minutes, recommendations, disciplinary records, membership lists and resignations, treasurer's records, pew deeds, IRS exemption information, title reports, financial records, budget reports, and audits. Promotional materials include a history of Phillips Church, and two scrapbooks containing programs, correspondence, news clippings, concert posters, holiday service notices, conference and lecture announcements, calendars, yearbooks, and business cards.
Arrangement
The Phillips Church records have been arranged into the two series listed below. Records in each series have been arranged chronologically by date created. When appropriate, similiar and continuous materials have been grouped together.
Series 1: Administrative records, 1823-2003
Series 2: Promotional materials, 1826-1928
Bibliography
Articles of Faith and Form of Covenant, adopted by the Phillips Church in South Boston. Together with the Names of The Members. "Formation." Kidder and Wright, 1841. 17.11.1 B65.5 PhiCC.
Articles of Faith and Form of Covenant, adopted by the Phillips Church of South Boston, Together with The Names of The Members. "History of Phillips Church." Wright & Potter, Printers, 1860. 17.11.1 B65.5 PhiCC.
Manual of the Phillips Church, Boston. "Historical Sketch." Alfred Mudge & Sons, Printers, 1882. 17.11.1 B65.5 PhiCC.
Seventy-Fifth Anniversary of Phillips Congregational Church, South Boston, Mass. "Historical Address" and "Anniversary Sermon." 1898. 17.11.1 B65.5 PhiCC.
Church correspondence.; Church discipline.; Church finance.; Church management.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Pews and pew rights.; Scrapbooks.; Evangelical Congregational Church (South Boston, Boston, Mass.); Phillips Church (South Boston, Boston, Mass.); South Boston (Boston, Mass.) -- Church history
- Administrative records, 1823 2003; 1823-2003; 8 Volumes; 13 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  The administrative records series contains church records, by-laws, statements of faith, correspondence, meeting minutes, recommendations, disciplinary records, membership lists and resignations, treasurer's records, pew deeds, IRS exemption information, financial records, budget reports, and audits.
  - Church records, 1823 1942; 1823-1842 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Church records, 1843 1860; 1843-1860 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Church records, 1860 1878; 1860-1878 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Church records, 1878 1892; 1878-1892 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Church records, 1892 1911; 1892-1911 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - List of subscribers, 1858 1866; 1858-1866 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pew deed map, 1859 (Folder 5)
  - Pew deeds, 1859 1911; 1859-1880 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Treasurer's records, 1860 1890; 1860-1890 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Treasurer's records, 1882 1888; 1882-1888 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Miscellaneous church records, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial records, 1954 2003; 1954, 1981-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - IRS exemption information, 1966 1983; 1966, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Disciplinary records, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Meeting minutes, recommendations, 1982 1997; 1982, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership lists, 1983 1985; 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Financial records, budget reports, audits, 1991 1998; 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Church records correspondence, 1996 1998; 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - By-laws, statements of faith, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Membership resignations, 1997 1998; 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Title report, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Promotional materials, 1826 1928; 1826-1928; 2 Volumes; 1 Folder
  The Promotional materials series contains a history of Phillips Church and two scrapbooks containing programs, correspondence, news clippings, concert posters, holiday service notices, conference and lecture announcements, calendars, yearbooks, and business cards.
  - Scrapbook, 1826 1905; 1826-1905 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1906 1913; 1906-1913 (Box 3)
  - History of Phillips Church, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)